A Finding Aid to the A Finding Aid to the Lawrence Fane Papers, circa 1964-2003, in the Archives of American Art AAA.fanelawr
Archives of American Art
Lawrence Fane papers
circa 1964-2003
AAA.fanelawr
Archives of American Art
0.4 Linear feet
The papers of New York sculptor Lawrence Fane measure 0.4 linear feet and date from circa 1964-2003. The collection primarily documents Lawrence Fane's activities as a sculptor through biographical material; printed material, including clippings, exhibition announcements, and catalogs; and photographs of artwork.
Fane, Lawrence
Provenance
The collection was donated by Lawrence Fane to the Archives of American Art in 2003.
Related Material
Also found at the Archives of American Art is an oral history interview with Lawrence Fane conducted by Albert Boime in 1982 on microfilm reel 4909.
Restrictions on Access
Use of original papers requires an appointment.
Biographical Note
Lawrence Fane (b. 1933) lives and works in New York and is known primarily as a sculptor.
Born in Kansas City, Missouri in 1933, Lawrence Fane moved to New York City in the mid-1960s. Fane attended Harvard University, where he received his Bachelor of Arts in 1955. He studied at the School of the Museum of Fine Arts in Boston, Massachusetts from 1955-1956; during this period, he served as an apprentice to the sculptor, George Demetrios.
Lawrence Fane has used various materials in constructing his sculptures, e.g., wood, bronze, and steel. He has described his work, primarily abstract in design, as evolving from studies of the human body to the landscape and its structural relationship to the body. Fane has exhibited in numerous solo and exhibitions in the United States and abroad: Bill Bace Gallery, Brooklyn Museum, Civici Musei 3 Gallerie di Storia e Arte, Colby College Museum of Art, de Cordova Museum, Galleria II Mercato del Sale, Kouros Gallery, Marilyn Pearl Gallery, Washington Art Gallery, and Zabriskie Gallery. In 2002, the University of Richmond Museum and the Muscarelle Museum in Virginia collaborated on twenty-five year retrospective of Fane's drawings and sculptures. Over the years, Fane has participated in group invitationals at the American Academy of Arts and Letters, Greater Hartford Council, the National Academy of Design, and New England Sculpture Association and other venues. He also participated in the Whitney Biennial Exhibition as a contributor to the Mark di Suvero Peace Tower.
Further, Fane has held teaching positions at the Rhode Island School of Design, 1963-1966 and Queens City, 1996-1998. Lawrence Fane has also been a visiting critic and lecturer at many colleges and universities throughout the United States including Boston University, Duke University, and the Yale School of Architecture.
Fane's work is in a number of public collections: the Brooklyn Museum, Corcoran Gallery of Art, Marsh Art Gallery, Museum of Contemporary Art in Udine, Italy, the Rhode Island School of Design, Weatherspoon Gallery, and the University of North Carolina, among others.
Lawrence Fane was awarded the Rome Prize by the American Academy in Rome for three consecutive years from 1960 to 1962. He has also received grants from the Ingram Merrill Foundation, 1984; New York Foundation for the Arts, 1997; and the Research Foundation, City University of New York, 1994 and 1996.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of New York sculptor Lawrence Fane measure 0.4 linear feet and date from circa 1964-2003. The collection primarily documents Lawrence Fane's activities as a sculptor through biographical material; printed material, including clippings, exhibition announcements, and catalogs; and photographs of artwork.
Biographical material includes curriculum vitae, artist's statement, brief narrative, and a bibliography.
Printed material contains clippings, exhibition announcements and catalogs. Clippings contain mostly reviews of Lawrence Fane's work. Exhibition announcements and catalogs document many of Fane's exhibitions, including the Bill Bace Gallery, Grounds for Sculpture, Kouros Gallery, Marilyn Pearl Gallery, University of Richmond Museums, and the Zabriskie Gallery.
Photographic material houses photographs, transparencies, slides, and reproductions of Lawrence Fane's artwork.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged as # series:
Series 1: Biographical Material, 1995-1998 (Box 1; folder 1)
Series 2: Printed Material, 1968-2003 (Box 1; 0.1 linear feet)
Series 3: Photographic Material, circa 1964-2003 (Box 1; 0.3 linear feet)
Bill Bace Gallery.; Grounds for Sculpture.; Kouros Gallery.; Marilyn Pearl Gallery; University of Richmond Museums.; Zabriskie Gallery.; Art teachers--New York (State)--New York; Photographs; Sculptors--New York (State)--New York--Interviews
- Biographical Material, 1995-1998; Series 1; (Box 1; 1 folder)
  Scope and Contents note
  This series contains curriculum vitae, an artist's statement, a brief narrative, and a bibliography of reviews of Lawrence Fane's work.
  - Biographical Material, 1995-1998 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Printed Material, 1968-2003; Series 2; (Box 1; 0.1 linear feet)
  This series includes clippings, exhibition announcements, and catalogs. Clippings primarily contain newspaper and periodical reviews of Lawrence Fane's work; there are scattered items, such as articles for reference use and a press release. Exhibition announcements and catalogs document the sculptor's solo and group exhibitions over a thirty year period.
  - Clippings, 1980-2003 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Exhibition Announcements, 1968-2002 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Catalogs, 1980-2002; (2 folders) (Box 1, Folder 4-5)
- Photographic Material, circa 1964-2003; Series 3; (Box 1; 0.3 linear feet)
  This series houses photographs, transparencies, and slides of Lawrence Fane's sculptures; also found are a few reproductions of the artist's work.
  - Photographs of Artwork, circa 1964-2003; (4 folders) (Box 1, Folder 6-9)
  - Transparencies of Artwork, circa 1986-1991 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Slides of Artwork, circa 1967-2003 (Box 1, Folder 11)